this enigma one machine manufactured in
the early 1940s for the German Wehrmacht
comes in its original oak case when I
unscrew the locking bolts and lift the
hinged lid the battery compartment is
visible on the right the state or the
three rotors and the reflector are
lettered with the B in red are visible
before a message was encoded these had
to be removed and programmed according
to the settings for the given day I lift
out the three rotors on their spindle
and slide each one off on the right side
of this rotor note the 26 brass
electrical contacts and the adjustable
ring and on the left the bakelite thumb
wheel I adjust the ring setting on one
of the rotors and reassemble the three
rotors in a new order on the spindle
each rotor has an identifying roman
rotor number finally i reinsert the
rotors on the spindle and lock the
entire assembly in place
note how the rightmost rotor advances
with each keystroke after one full
revolution the rotor to the left will
advance by one position resetting the
pattern of the electrical contacts a
further level of security is provided by
the front plug board or sticker Brett
there are 26 double sockets and 13
cables each with two pins the German
military generally used 10 cables here
all 13 are attached finally I close the
machine lid and the front flap of the
case to ensure that the cables are
correctly positioned next we set the
power supply to external and set the
rotors to the three-letter key for the
day
let's type in the word enigma
when the e is pressed the bulb for J
turns on and the right-hand rotor
advances one increment similarly n
becomes t ir g.b.m e and a/c in this
segment we see how the rotor turns with
each keystroke the hair marked version
of the Enigma machine used numbered
positions for each letter not the
letters themselves each number
corresponds to a letter of the alphabet
a is o1 b o 2 and so on
to decode i reset the rotors to the
initial position in practice the
operator would provide a new encoded
setting in the message
note how in decipherment j becomes e the
TN the RI until our original worm
one-word plaintext enigma is revealed
you